Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
Computer architecture for everybody. So now
What we're going to do is we're going to do
The single instruction CPU. And so before we
Walk through the counter circuit and the counter
Basically takes an adder and a register and takes
The outputs of the register, one of the inputs
Of the adder and then hardcodes the other one
To one. So it's like an increment instruction.
Okay? So it's incrementing whatever was in the
Register and then we have a clock and once the
Clock starts it starts doing its increment thing.
So you can see I it's running low to high low
To high and then it every on every clock pulse
The registers goes up by one and the speed of
Our clock is 1 second and again what we did is
We made a simple wristwatch but this is like a
Wristwatch this is not a programmable CPU. So
What I talked about in lecture is I talked about
The simplest possible two instruction CPU. So we
Need something where it does something different
Based on input from the outside world. What did
I happen there? Instruction. Did I type it wrong?
Yeah. Okay. So here we have an instruction. This
Is the in the the single instruction computer.
I'm going to let's add another output here.
So we can watch the clock going high and low just
Just so that you can see that clock going high and
Low. so the clock is high and so it's copied
This in. So it's exactly like the counter except
It has some decode logic. We think of this in a
CPU as decode logic where we have an instruction
And that instruction can be either a zero or a
One and when the instruction is a zero we are
Clearing the register. So let's go ahead and start
The clock and so now the register is zero and so
The we're the instruction is zero. So the way
It works is the output of the adder is in effect
Blocked because we're taking the output of an
Adder and running it through three and gates. And
Then the input to the register is all zeros when
The instruction is zero. That's the reset case.
And as soon as we type the instruction, set the
Instruction to one, then it becomes an increment
Instruction. And so you can now see the thing we
Saw before except the ANDgates the decode logic is
Seeing an instruction that is increment and it's
Now passing every second it's passing through the
Data from the output and now we're doing just the
Increment but it's incrementing but only when the
Instruction is one. So as soon as I So that's like
One instruction, one instruction, one instruction,
One instruction, and now oh now your instruction
Are a reset. And so no matter what the value was
As the clock continues to click, it's running
Reset instructions, which is setting the register
To zero. And again, all it's really doing is every
Time the clock ticks, it's copying from the inputs
Into the register, but because the AND gates are
Suppressing the output of the adder in a sense,
They're blocking it. And so let's go ahead and
Send some increment instructions. Increment,
Increment, increment, increment, increment.
And so you'll see that it copies it and away
It goes. And so that is our little two instruction
Central processing unit with a one second, one
Hertz clock. It's adding one. Hey, so let's just
Do something fun. Let's just add two. Let's
Let's tell it to stop first. Oh, wait, wait. Oh,
Crap. I didn't mean to delete it. , hey, wait. I
Can reload it again. Here we go. Let's reload the
Instruction circuit. I deleted it. That's a good
Reason to save and reload it. See how easy that
Was? , okay. So, , so let's go ahead and let's
I'll have the clock be off. So what I'm going to
Do is I'm going to delete this input and I'm going
To put the input here on from to the two. So now
We're going to be adding two. It's going to be
Like 2 4 6 8 kind of a thing. Now we have to put
A one here because that so that's like B1 is zero,
B2 is one, and B3 is zero. So that's adding two.
So you'll notice we're not even starting yet
Because the register has the value of zero inside
Of it and it's sending that to the adder and the
Adder is adding zero on the A's plus two on the
B's. And so it's got 0 plus two. So now we're
Going to have a counter that counts 2 4 6 8 which
Is too high and overflows and then two 4 0 2 4 6
Overflow I think is what we're going to get. So
Let's turn this baby on. So the clock is starting
But we still are sending the clear instruction. So
The two is being ignored because the AND gates the
Decode logic in this little baby CPU is blocking
It. So let's go ahead and turn it into the
Increment and we'll start seeing this thing go up
By two 02 clock clock 4. So we're making a we're
Making an adder that counts by twos. Six. The next
Thing will be overflow. And it's a zero again,
Right? And so it goes 0 2 4 6 overflow. 0 2 4 6
Overflow. Okay. And so I hope that you found
This little thing interesting. You don't have
To do it. You could you can build it. It's not
That hard to build. It's it just is this one's
A little hard because you got all these little
Wires. You got to get them to look pretty. But
That's what these way points are for. , but you
Can always just load one up and then play with it
Yourself. Okay, cheers. H. , see you on the net.